Guide to the James Baldwin Early Manuscripts and Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
James Baldwin early manuscripts and papers
1941-1945
JWJ MSS 21
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.7
(6 boxes)
An early group of materials by Baldwin, including manuscripts, correspondence, artworks and personal papers. Among the manuscripts are drafts of a novel, "Crying Holy", which evolved much later into Baldwin's first published novel, "Go Tell It On the Mountain." The correspondence includes letters from Baldwin's friends in the military, including Tom Martin. Some of the artwork, mostly pencil sketches, is by Baldwin while a number of other items are by a high school friend of his, Martin Weissman. Among the personal papers is one photograph of a very young Baldwin.
Baldwin, James, 1924-1987
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Bart Kaplan, 1998.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Restricted Fragile in Box 6 may only be consulted with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies or photographic prints for reference use have been substituted in the main files.
JAMES BALDWIN, 1924-1987
The life of James Baldwin, novelist, essayist and civil rights advocate, has been described in a number of biographies and critical works, including David Leeming's James Baldwin: A Biography [Viking Penguin, 1994] and James Campbell's Talking at the Gates: A Life of James Baldwin [Faber, 1991 and Viking, 1991]
The provenance of the papers is a matter of some intrigue. The donor, Bart Kaplan, acquired the papers through eminent domain, after his company took possession of a storage building in downtown Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, sometime in the early 1960s. The space in which they were stored had apparently once belonged to a publishing company which had left behind a suitcase containing these materials from James Baldwin. The relationship between Baldwin and the publishing company, as well as how a small parcel of his earliest literary effects was left with them, is uncertain. According to several sources, the materials in this archive were known to have been created by Baldwin, but were thought discarded or simply forgotten. In his introduction to New Essays on Go Tell It on the Mountain [Cambridge UP, 1996], Trudier Harris indicates that, following Harper's rejection of a draft section of "In My Father's House" [alternately "Crying Holy"], Baldwin put the manuscript "in a 'duffel bag'" and turned his attention to another project. Other circumstantial evidence - the dating of the first draft of "Crying Holy" to November 1941, while Baldwin was still in high school, and the length of the typescript version (57 pages - a few shy of the 60-page manuscript Richard Wright urged Baldwin to submit to Harper's) - suggests that this recovered cache of material fills in the gap that bibliographers have noted.
Scope and Contents
The James Baldwin Early Manuscripts and Papers contain material documenting a short period of Baldwin's young adult life between 1941-1945, when Baldwin was just beginning his literary career. The material has been organized into four series: Writings, Correspondence, Artwork, and Personal Papers.
Series I, Writings (1941-45, n.d.), consists of works by Baldwin and other writers. The various draft stages of Baldwin's "Crying Holy" include at least two distinct plotlines. The first group of drafts, focusing on the subtitle "The Prisoner", concern a plot which varies from the final version of the decade-long project which culminated in Go Tell it on the Mountain in 1953. The second group of drafts, "The Sacrifice" et seq., follows more closely with the themes and characters of the finished novel. Other works by Baldwin are a section of an untitled short story featuring the characters Julius Greenberg and Mark Hayward, notes for a play entitled "Vanguard", a folder of poetry, including a lengthy narrative poem, and an issue (missing its cover) of what is likely to be The Magpie, the literary magazine of Baldwin's alma mater, De Witt Clinton High School, featuring several items by Baldwin.
Writings of Others includes two folders of material by Werner Loeb - poems, press releases, short stories, and play scenarios, evidently written for a school class. The unidentified writings at the end of the series are in several different hands and include poetry, essays, and stories.
Series II, Correspondence (1941-45, n.d.), contains principally letters addressed to Baldwin between 1941 and 1945. Many of these are addressed to Baldwin by friends serving in the military, including Sheldon Beigel, Paul Gertz, and Arthur Moore. A series of letters from 1944 is from Tom Martin, with whom Baldwin had lived during his brief stay in New Jersey in 1942-43. There are two drafts of outgoing letters, apparently in the hand of Baldwin. One is most likely to Tom Martin, while the other is to a "Dan'l". There are also two letters signed with this name only in the "Unidentified" folder.
Among the third-party letters is one addressed to "Sister" by James's brother, David Baldwin. Remaining letters are a rejection form letter from Harper's Magazine and a letter of recommendation for Baldwin from a Clinton High School advisor.
The majority of the pieces in Series III, Artwork (1945, n.d.) are not by James Baldwin, though there are a few pencil doodles which were found with manuscripts he wrote. Identified artwork includes one folder of watercolor sketches by "Leon K." and a group of ink sketches and etching proofs by Martin Weissman, a high school friend of Baldwin's. The remaining pieces, principally academic studies and sketches are unidentified.
The varied assortment of items which make up Series IV, Personal Papers (1943-45, n.d.), provides a snapshot of Baldwin's early life in New York. Here are a bank book, military papers (some of which document Baldwin's attachment to the Office of War Information), notices from PM Magazine (another temporary assignment for Baldwin), a single photograph of what appears to be a very young James Baldwin, and tax documents from 1944. The group of printed items consists mainly of issues of small-circulation newsletters for Socialist organizations. A few of these bear a mailing label for Martin Weissman.
African Americans in literature; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Baldwin, James, 1924-1987; Weissman, Martin
- Writings, 1941-45, n.d.; Series I; 0.4' (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Writings, is divided into two subseries and arranged alphabetically by title or author.
  - WRITINGS BY JAMES BALDWIN
    - "Crying Holy"
      - Synopsis, typescript and holograph, corrected (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - "Glad Tidings: Book 1: The Prisoner", draft, holograph, 1941 Nov (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - "Crying Holy: Prologue -- The Prisoner," draft typescript, corrected, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - "The Prologue to Crying Holy," draft, holograph and typescript, corrected (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - "The Prisoner," draft, typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
        With original folder
      - "Crying Holy: Book 1 [The Prisoner]," draft, holograph, corrected, 1941 Nov (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - "Crying Holy: Book I: The Sacrifice," draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - "Glad Tidings," draft pages, typescript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - "Crying Holy: Book I: The Sacrifice," notes, 1945 Feb 4 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - "Book II / In My Father's House," draft pages, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Untitled draft beginning: "Gabriel Grimes, negro, born 1884...", holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Untitled draft beginning: "Gabriel Grimes, negro, born 1884...", typescript, and carbon corrected (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
        [lacking page 7]
      - Mailing envelope for manuscript, 1945 Apr 27 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Untitled story, re: Julius Greenberg and Mark Hayward, holograph, corrected (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Poems, holograph and typescript, corrected (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - With original folder labelled: "WORK-IN-PROGRESS" and "Ignorant Armies"
    - "Vanguard: A Play in One Act", notes, holograph, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
      With doodles
    - Printed works from issue of The Magpie[?] [De Witt Clinton High School literary magazine], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Includes: "Judgment Day" [poem]
      "Youth" [poem]
      "Mississippi Legend" [short story]
      "Incident in London" [short story]
  - WRITINGS OF OTHERS
    - Loeb, Werner, 1943, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
      Includes: poems, press releases, short stories and play scenarios, typescript, corrected
    - Unidentified
      - Essay: "Then expansion strain-lateral...", typescript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Essay on Joseph Conrad, J. M. Barrie and W. H. Hudson, holograph (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Poetry fragments, holograph and typescript (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Short story: "It was late; very late; about eleven o'clock," mimeograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Story fragments re: military argument in restaurant, typescript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Correspondence, 1941-45, n.d.; Series II; 0.2' (1 box)
  Series II, Correspondence, is arranged alphabetically.
  - Alexander, Dot (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - American Negro Theatre, 1945 Apr (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Beigel, Sheldon, 1943-44 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Includes: draft of response by James Baldwin and draft of letter to "David" in unidentified hand
  - Carlson, Esther, 1945 Jun (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - [Darling?], ---, 1944 Dec 14 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Gertz, Paul, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - James, Stephen D., 1944 Nov (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Envelope only
  - Lloyd, David [agent], 1942 Jun 25 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - MacLow, Jackson, 1944 Dec 16 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Martin, Tom, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Mehlman, Roy, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Moore, Arthur, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Palakian, Rose, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - United States. Office of War Information, 1945 Jan 3 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - [Weissman?], Martin, 1944 Mar 31 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Young People's Socialist League, 1944, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Unidentified, 1944, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Draft of letter: James Baldwin to Tom [Martin?], 1944 Sep 2 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Draft of letter: James Baldwin to "Dan'l", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Third-party letters, 1944-45 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    Includes: Baldwin, David, to "Sister"
    "Marge" to John Matysuk
    "Mother" to Louis Weinberg
    Socialist Party, Manhattan Committee to Lois Davis
  - Rejection form letter, Harper's Magazine, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Letter of recommendation for James Baldwin to the Editor of the Amsterdam Star-News from Wilmer T. Stone, faculty advisor, "The Magpie", DeWitt Cinton High School, 1941 Oct 16 (Box 2, Folder 47)
- Artwork, 1945, n.d.; Series III; 0.2' (1 box)
  Series III, Artwork, is listed by type of material.
  - Pencil doodles [by James Baldwin?], n.d. (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Watercolor sketches by "Leon K.", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Ink sketches and etching proofs by Martin ["Mottke"] Weissman, 1945, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Ink sketches, unidentified artists, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Ink and pencil sketches on onion-skin paper, unidentified artists (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Ink and pencil sketches (after Picasso and Weber; life studies), unidentified artists (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Watercolor sketches, unidentified artists, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 54)
- Personal Papers, 1943-45, n.d.; Series IV; 0.2' (1 box)
  Series IV, Personal Papers, is arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Advertising booklet: Bocour colors, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Bank book, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Clippings, 1945, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Label "Schapiro's", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Military papers, 1943-45 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Notes, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Notices from PM Magazine, 1945 Feb (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Paper and envelopes, blank (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Photograph: [James Baldwin as young child?], n.d. (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Postcard set: Roualt paintings, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Printed items, 1943-45 (Box 4, Folder 65-67)
    Includes issues of:
    Challenge! [Young People's Socialist League]; Enquiry: A Journal of Independent Radical Thought
    The Key Reporter [Phi Beta Kappa] Labor Action; New Yorker; Senior Scholastic
    War Commentary [For Anarchism]; Why?: A Bulletin of Free Inquiry; Zionist Review
  - Tax documents, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 68)
- Oversize, 1.5' (1 box)
  - Artwork: Ink sketch, unidentified artist, n.d. (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 69)
- Restricted Fragile Papers
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folder 3 (Box 6, Folder 70)
  - Box 1, folder 4 (Box 6, Folder 71)
  - Box 1, folder 12 (Box 6, Folder 72)
  - Box 1, folder 13 (Box 6, Folder 73)
  - Box 1, folder 16 (Box 6, Folder 74)
  - Box 1, folder 19 (Box 6, Folder 75)
  - Box 1, folder 23 (Box 6, Folder 76)
  - Box 1, folder 25 (Box 6, Folder 77)
  - Box 2, folder 44 (Box 6, Folder 78)